- AAMIR TAAKI: It's no longer
the era of industry.
We're in a technological era,
fundamentally.
The fascists, they have
the resources.
But we have imagination.
We are making the tools to take
back our sovereignty.
When we make a giant
"fuck you" to the system,
it's breaking that stranglehold
on the tools of power
that's used against us.
The fascists always use
the narrative of,
"We are the white knights
in shining armor
"protecting against the threats.
We come here and we move out
the dark with pure whiteness."
That's a false narrative,
because there is corruption
in those castles.
The real base of
power lies with us.
We are the darkness.
- MALE NEWSCASTER: A trial,
which potentially,
could have very
far-reaching implications
has just started
in New York City.
- MALE NEWSCASTER #2: A jury
will decide a case
that could impact the future
of internet privacy.
- FEMALE REPORTER: Thousands
of drugs came through
the black website
called "Silk Road."
- MAN: The government
overstepped their boundaries
to acquire the info
they claim they have.
- This is not going away.
- This is gonna be
the biggest takedown
of what is currently
in existence.
- KEANU REEVES NARRATING:
On January 13, 2015,
a criminal trial began
for the accused leader
of the Silk Road,
a black market in an area
of the internet
known as "the deep web."
The deep web is vast,
thousands of times larger
than the visible internet,
what's called the "surface web."
But the deep web is not a place.
It simply accounts for all of
the unindexed content online...
Banking data, administrative
code for governments,
corporations and universities.
It's like looking under
the hood of the internet.
Over time, the deep web
became inhabited
by people of all types
who wanted to use this
terrain for privacy.
This hidden area of the deep web
is called the "dark net"
and it's accessible with
a software service called "Tor,"
originally developed
by the US military
and now open source
and publicly funded.
And while law enforcement
and the media
have painted a picture
that Tor and the dark net
are nefarious tools
for criminals,
it's important to
understand that they are
largely used for good by
government agencies, journalists
and dissidents around the world.
- REEVES NARRATING:
In the summer of 2011,
an ad for the Silk Road
appeared on the dark net.
The Silk Road was an underground
exchange for any type of goods,
but mostly it was
used for drugs.
There have always been
drug markets online,
but none with the scale,
sophistication
and ease of use
as the Silk Road.
It would not remain
underground for long.
- MALE NEWSCASTER: Hundreds
of thousands of users
use the impossible-to-trace
website which sells drugs,
forged documents
and even hit men.
It's called the Silk Road.
Just look at some
of the 13,000 items
offered through
that underground site.
Ultra clean cocaine,
clean and real LSD,
high grade MDMA,
also known as "Molly"...
All with fast and free shipping.
It generated roughly
$1.2 billion in sales
with nearly 960,000 users,
both buyers and sellers,
in the US and more than a dozen
other countries worldwide.
YouTube videos like this one
with 15,000 views
tell anyone how to download
an untraceable technology
known as Tor that pulls data
from thousands
of computers worldwide
to create this wide
open marketplace.
- MALE NEWSCASTER ♪2: This
hidden internet is underpinned
by a virtual currency
called "Bitcoin."
Bitcoins offer anonymized
transactions,
which can be almost impossible
for the police to trace.
- MAN: Heroin, opium, cannabis,
ecstasy, psychedelics,
stimulants, opioids...
And here they are.
So, oxycodone, all of those.
Codeine, black tar heroin.
You name it, they have it.
They're all listed in the...
in the light of day.
It's unbelievable.
- REEVES NARRATING:
The Silk Road's success
was largely due to an innovative
combination of Tor and Bitcoin.
Bitcoin is a technology that
uses cryptographic code
to create digital currency.
The sender transmits their
Bitcoin code through a ledger
called the "block chain"
to arrive at the recipient.
Bitcoin is not
perfectly anonymous.
But if used carefully, it
facilitates online purchases
without revealing identity.
Bitcoin was an ideal currency
for the Silk Road,
because it allows for anonymity
and is outside the control
of banks and governments.
- MAN: I really became
aware of the Silk Road
when Adrian Chen at Gawker,
uh, did his profile.
I think in a way,
that story, as much as
it documented the Silk Road,
it created the Silk Road, too.
I mean it... it drove so
many people to the site.
I think it probably was
an order of magnitude increase
in users on the Silk Road.
So from that point on, I felt
like I had missed the story
and I... I wanted the next big
story on the Silk Road.
But I was also just fascinated
with the community that was,
you know, being created there.
EBay doesn't have that
kind of user community.
This was like a really
tight-knit movement of people.
It was a fascinating thing
just to lurk around in.
- MAN: It's a certifiable,
one-stop shop for illegal drugs
that represents
the most brazen attempt
to peddle drugs online
that we have ever seen.
It's more brazen than anything
else by light-years.
- I mean, they had a really big,
you know, target on their back.
And they even had been taunting,
to some extent, law enforcement
and, you know, the powers that
be by doing this in the open.
And that's actually part of what
this marketplace is all about.
It's not so much about selling
drugs as much as it is to say,
to make a political
statement of sorts, right?
"This shouldn't be prohibited.
"We're free to do what we want
"and we have
the technology to do it.
So there."
- REEVES NARRATING:
The news around the Silk Road
came almost entirely
from law enforcement
and government officials
with little insight from those
who were behind
the market itself.
So the core architects
and vendors of the Silk Road
were sought out using encryption
keys to verify their identities
and preserving their anonymity.
This is the first time
they have spoken publicly.
- [digitally-altered voice]
- REEVES NARRATING:
The Silk Road didn't appear
to have a single leader.
There were the regular posts
from the systems administrator,
but otherwise the service
appeared to be
primarily community-run.
Then on February 5, 2012,
after a highly successful
first year of business,
the Silk Road administrator
made an announcement...
- You're the Dread Pirate
Roberts, admit it.
- With pride.
- REEVES NARRATING:
The Dread Pirate Roberts
was cribbed from the mythical
character from the novel
and film "The Princess Bride,"
and the choice was no accident.
In the original story
by William Goldman,
the Dread Pirate Roberts
was a nom de guerre handed down
from user to user and passed
along eternally.
- The man I inherited it from
was not the real
Dread Pirate Roberts either.
The real Roberts has
been retired 15 years
and I have been
Roberts ever since.
I shall retire and hand
the name over to someone else.
- REEVES NARRATING: This Dread
Pirate Roberts, or DPR,
would come to spearhead
the Silk Road forums and was
generally assumed to be the
creator and owner of the site.
- The Dread Pirate Roberts
to me seemed to be
kind of the most interesting
figure in that whole world.
On the Silk Road forums,
he was constantly posting
these manifestos and love
letters to his users
and Libertarian
philosophical treaties.
And he even had like this, uh,
Dread Pirate Roberts book club
where he hosted discussions
of Austrian economics
and free market philosophy.
At the same time,
nobody knew who he was.
He had never spoken
to the press before.
I approached him on the Silk
Road forum mid-2012 and, uh,
started kind of just like trying
to persuade him to talk,
chipping away at him and just
bugging him constantly.
- GREENBERG:
The actual trigger,
I think that made him
decide to talk
was this competing dark
website called "Atlantis."
They were really
much more aggressive
in their marketing
than the Silk Road.
They put out this YouTube video
advertising Atlantis
as the... the new, better
dark web drug site.
So when I went back to
the Dread Pirate Roberts
and said, "You know,
I'm going to do this story.
It can either be about Atlantis
or it can be about you,"
I think he realized that,
you know, that...
He was a savvy business
guy who realized
he had to talk at that point.
He did have a kind
of political message
that he wanted to get out,
and I could see that
in what he was posting
on the forums.
So I kind of played up to that
and I told him like,
"I can be the... the vessel
for you to talk about
what the Silk Road
really represents,"
and I think that
that appealed to him.
So it took eight months,
but finally he did agree
to an interview.
- GREENBERG: Of course he...
he didn't tell me anything
about himself... where he lives,
you know, his age, identity,
uh, anything that could
be remotely identifying.
- REEVE SPEAKING AS DPR:
"I didn't start the Silk Road.
"My predecessor did.
"From what I understand it was
an original idea to combine
"Bitcoin and Tor to create
an anonymous market.
"Everything was in place.
He just put the pieces together.
"The most I'm willing
to reveal is that I am not
the first administrator
of Silk Road."
- He was incredibly
secretive, of course,
about the inner workings
of the Silk Road and,
you know, his own identity,
of course.
I mean he was hunted by
every law enforcement agency
that you can imagine.
- REEVES SPEAKING AS DPR:
"The management of Silk Road
"is a collaborative effort.
"It's not just me making sure
Silk Road runs smoothly.
"More often than not,
the best ideas
come from the community itself."
- But he did tell me like
some interesting things
about how he viewed
himself and his... and...
and the way that
the Silk Road works.
- REEVES SPEAKING AS DPR:
"We don't allow the sale
"of anything that's main purpose
is to harm innocent people
"or that it was necessary
"to harm innocent people
to bring to market.
"For example, anything
stolen is forbidden.
"Counterfeit money and coupons
"which are used
to defraud people.
"Hit men aren't allowed and
neither is child pornography.
No substance on Silk Road falls
under those guidelines."
- This went beyond just,
you know,
like legalizing marijuana
or even heroin.
He wanted to see a... a new
relationship between individuals
and the government,
where the government was,
you know, basically hamstrung
and couldn't control
what people bought and sold.
- REEVES SPEAKING AS DPR:
"At its core, Silk Road is a way
"to get around regulation
from the state.
"The state tries to control
nearly every aspect
"of our lives,
not just drug use.
"Anywhere they do that,
there's an opportunity
to live your life as you see
fit, despite their efforts."
- I guess I shouldn't generally
say this kind of thing,
but I really liked
the Dread Pirate Roberts
that I interviewed.
I thought he was, you know, uh,
a really super-interesting guy
with a really
coherent philosophy.
He came across to me as
this kind of middle-aged,
wise man figure, you know?
- REEVES NARRATING:
But not everyone on Silk Road
believed in Libertarian
philosophy.
Bringing an end to
the drug war was the agenda
that truly united the community.
- [digitally-altered voice]
- I could see that the Silk Road
wasn't just another
cyber-criminal scheme.
This was a guy who saw himself
as the leader of a movement.
- REEVES SPEAKING AS DPR:
"One thing I've learned
"playing Dread Pirate Roberts
is that your actions
"are sure to please some
and infuriate others.
"But we can't stay
silent forever.
"We have an important message.
"And the time is ripe for
the world to hear it.
"What we're doing
isn't about scoring drugs
"or sticking it to the man.
"It's about standing up for
our rights as human beings
"and refusing to submit when
we've done no wrong.
"Silk Road is a vehicle
for that message.
All else is secondary."
- The Silk Road
functioned because
the Dread Pirate Roberts
was trusted.
At any point, he could have
shut down the Silk Road
and run away with
everyone's Bitcoins.
We've seen that happen
with a bunch of other
dark web businesses.
And I think people believed that
he wouldn't because they felt
that he was a true believer
in this kind of radically
Libertarian, crypto-anarchic
philosophy that, you know,
goes back to the cypherpunks
of the 1990s.
- REEVES NARRATING: Twenty-five
years ago, in the Bay Area,
a burgeoning group of
mathematicians,
crypto-anarchists and hackers
began to meet in
each other's homes.
This tight-knit group
came to be casually
known as the "cypherpunks."
These original members were
not socially motivated,
but more concerned
with the hard math
of cryptographic technology
and the broader philosophy
of anonymity,
individual liberty and privacy.
- The government has
this clear policy of
access to all plain text,
meaning whatever you're saying...
They want access to.
If it's stored on your hard
disk, they want access to it.
If it so goes over the wire,
they want access to it.
If you are proxying speech
for someone else,
they wanna know who it is.
- REEVES NARRATING: The
cypherpunks were instrumental
in the growing movement towards
privacy and anonymity online.
And they would pioneer the way
into the hidden corners
of the internet.
- Maybe the big turning point
for the cypherpunks,
I think, was WikiLeaks
and Julian Assange
and Jacob Appelbaum's idea
of what it means
to be a cypherpunk.
- You cannot trust a government
to implement the policies
that it says that
it's implementing.
And so we must provide
the underlying tools,
secret cryptographic codes
that the government
couldn't spy on
to everyone as a sort
of use of force.
And a government no matter
how hard it tries,
if the cyphers are good,
uh, cannot break into your
communications directly.
- Force of authority
is derived from violence.
One must acknowledge
with cryptography,
no amount of violence will ever
solve a math problem.
- ASSANGE: Exactly.
- And this is the important key.
It doesn't mean you
can't be tortured.
It doesn't mean that they can't
try to bug your house
or subvert it in some way,
but it means if they find
an encrypted message
it doesn't matter if they have
the force of the authority
behind everything that they do.
They cannot solve
that math problem.
- This movement is not
about the destruction of law.
- CROWD: This movement is not
- It is about
the construction of law.
- GREENBERG: These are guys
who want to create
encryption tools that
everybody can use.
It's not just for the elite.
It's... it's trying to shift
the way that the internet works
to provide secrecy and anonymity
and privacy to everyone,
you know, so like, um, it's
a much more populist movement.
- There is a community
of people in the security
and cryptography space
who want to live in a world
where the government cannot
record their emails,
cannot listen to
their telephone calls,
cannot see who they're
spending time with.
And they're trying
to build tools.
They're trying to build
protocols and services
that can facilitate
that kind of anonymous
and private exchange
of information.
- I actually think this
all comes down to
wanting to live a free life.
And the recognition which really
predates all technology,
that an observed life is not
a completely free life,
that a zone of privacy
is just a core human value.
And the technology to me
is just an incarnation
of those basic human values.
And I think that the people who
are trying to build currencies
that are free of tracking
and government control
and technologies that let you
have a private conversation
and those kinds of things are
just people who are seeing that
the technology can both enable
and disable that space.
- MAN: There are more
cypherpunks than ever before.
They want to entirely cripple
the government's ability
to enforce law.
They want cryptography
to make the rules
instead of law enforcement.
- REEVES NARRATING: Cody Wilson
is a crypto-anarchist
best known for developing
the Liberator,
a 3D printable gun
that was downloaded
100,000 times in two days.
- When a group of
baby boomers are told,
okay now 3D printers
will print guns,
they can do nothing but say,
"Well, it's been nice living
in the world I used to know."
We want to question
the very foundation,
evacuate the very foundation
that this order, moral, ethical,
political, is founded on.
- [gunshot firing]
- WILSON: To see beyond
good and evil
and to allow something
else to happen.
This is where the figure of DPR
is so interesting to me.
Like is he a liberal?
Like is he a Misesian
like he says he is?
Oh, he believes in Libertarian
market principles,
and you know man against
the state and all these...
these principles
of freedom and axioms of...
Or... or is he someone else?
Like... like who I hope
he is or someone
like I would try to hope to be,
who's just looking for
a way, a mechanism,
to help peek beyond good
and evil a little bit.
And is he more enthusiastic
about what he's...
what he's allowed to be opened
up, the doors he's opening.
- GREENBERG: Of course,
there will be
a dark side to the dark web.
And if we want to enable this...
this true crypto-
anarchic future,
anyone who's working on that,
I think, has to reckon with
the fact that they're going to
be enabling really nasty things
along with this kind of
information freedom revolution
that they're taking part in.
- REEVES NARRATING: By August
2012, business was booming.
The Silk Road had become
a thriving, anonymous
and unregulated black market.
The internet being
used in this way,
posed a major threat
to the government,
greater perhaps
than selling drugs.
- Even as a... a law
enforcement officer,
I still wouldn't know where to
go and buy crack on the streets
or buy heroin, but I do know
how to go online and find it.
It's downloading some software
and... and the next thing
you know you're there
and you can purchase a service
or drugs very easily.
- MALE NEWSCASTER: Since
when does a teenager
become obsessed with
the daily mail delivery?
Fidgeting and pacing made
this Fisher's mom suspicious.
So when her family's mail
arrived, she grabbed it
and found a cartoon DVD box
addressed to her son
with something extra...
A package of white crystals.
So she confronted
her 14-year-old
and both their lives
changed forever.
- I don't think anybody really
cared in law enforcement
until Senator Schumer went,
"Oh, my God, we've gotta do
something about this."
- Today I'm calling on the DEA
and the Department of Justice
to immediately shut this site
down before more damage is done.
- SHIPLEY: Because if you think
about what law enforcement
at the federal level has
to do to even start a case,
I don't think this case
would have been started
if it wasn't for some
political impetus by, you know,
a senator saying,
"We need to look into this."
- The FBI today shut down
what it's calling
the most sophisticated
internet site
in the business of
selling hard drugs,
including heroin,
cocaine and LSD.
Anyone trying to log
on to the website today
found this notice:
"Shut down by the FBI."
- MALE NEWSCASTER: It was
a sophisticated electronic
smokescreen and it took federal
agents almost two years.
- WOMAN: They were able to
infiltrate the site,
but they made some of these
purchases themselves
using undercover identities.
- The secretive
Dread Pirate Roberts
was arrested in the most
unlikely of places...
This local public library in
this San Francisco neighborhood.
- MALE NEWSCASTER:
The FBI seized $3.6 million
of Bitcoin's biggest haul
in its five-year history.
- When the criminal complaint
first appeared in October,
it describes this 29-year-old
kid named Ross Ulbricht.
Not only do they say that he has
run this billion-dollar plus
black market conspiracy and they
accuse him of drug trafficking
and money laundering and somehow
computer hacking charges,
as well, which is
something that I had
never associated with
the Silk Road.
But then also in this criminal
complaint there is outlined
his plot to pay for the murders
of a potential informant
and a blackmailer.
- MALE NEWSCASTER: It seems
at least one Silk Road user
threatened to reveal
the identities
of thousands of others.
So investigators say
Ulbricht tried to execute
a Murder-For-Hire on that user,
offering $150,000 to a would-be
hit man because...
- It threw me for a loop.
It was really not
the Dread Pirate Roberts
that I had ever imagined.
This connection between
Ross Ulbricht,
who plenty of evidence suggests
that he was involved
in the Silk Road.
They, after all,
seized his laptop
while he was logged
in to the Silk Road.
He was caught red-handed.
But these two personalities,
these two personas,
do seem to be almost
schizophrenic.
It's so difficult to imagine
that they are the same person.
- And so the FBI's whole case
is based on the idea
if they can show that Dread
Pirate Roberts is Ross Ulbricht?
- Right. That's... that's
the most important part, right?
Because he was trying to hide
his identity
on the site as well.
So the first thing
they're gonna have to do
is definitively link him as
the person who runs the site.
- Oh, man, it was like it
was yesterday, actually.
I was on my computer and,
um, I was on Facebook.
And there's this guy that I know
and he's very into like Bitcoin
and cryptocurrencies
and stuff like that.
He posted this article and it
says, "Ross Ulbricht Arrested."
And I pull up Lyn's, uh,
g-chat and I'm like,
"What is going on?
Like why is..."
And I'm looking at Ross' page...
Picture, you know,
about being arrested.
What is this?
She says, "We don't even know.
We're leaving Costa Rica
right now."
I mean, they were on their way,
but it blew my mind.
I mean totally blew my mind.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Ross William Ulbricht grew up
in a suburb of Austin,
the only son of Kirk and Lyn
with an older sister
named Callie.
It's a loving, tight-knit,
middle-class family.
The Ulbrichts earn their income
from properties they built
and rent on
the Costa Rican coast.
Ross was an avid outdoorsman,
an Eagle Scout like his father,
and displayed
an early aptitude for math.
Ross earned a full scholarship
to the University of Texas
at Dallas studying Physics.
He graduated in 2006 and then
won another full scholarship
to Penn State
to pursue a Masters
in Material Science
and Engineering.
It was at Penn State that
Ross began a deep interest
in Libertarianism, particularly
the work of Ludwig von Mises
and the Austrian School
of Economics.
Yet by 2009,
having completed his Masters,
Ross seemed to be having
a change of life plan
telling his mother
he no longer had an interest
in pursuing a career in science
and instead wanted to
become an entrepreneur.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Ross moved back to Austin
and opened his own used book
company, Good Wagon,
donating a portion of
the proceeds to an inner city
youth program and to
a prison literacy project.
- I remember him saying,
when we had coffee,
the last time we saw each other,
I remember him saying
that he wished he had joined
a fraternity in college.
And I remember saying,
"Well, that's surprising."
You know, I didn't really
understand that perspective,
um, and I just remember him
thinking, well he focused a lot
on his studies in school and
maybe didn't create the social
network that he was looking
for, um, in... in school.
But as far as where we saw each
other going or where we saw
ourselves going, um, I think
we both had a strong desire
to be in control of our destiny.
You know, again like when
he started the book company,
uh, totally natural.
Not even something that
I would have questioned,
where there are a lot of people
that would never start
their own business.
But for Ross, sure,
you know, why not?
- REEVES NARRATING:
But the business floundered
and Ross eventually
shut it down.
And if a post on his Linkedln
page was any indication,
Ross had experienced
a kind of epiphany
on the next way forward.
Ulbricht wrote,
"Now my goals have shifted.
"I want to use economic theory
as a means to abolish
"the use of coercion and
aggression amongst mankind.
"To that end, I am creating
an economic simulation to give
"people a first-hand experience
of what it would be like
to live in a world without
the systemic use of force."
From this moment, in late 2010,
Ross became something
of a free spirit,
eventually leaving
his parents' home in Austin
to live with his sister Callie
in Sydney, Australia
and then returning
briefly to Austin.
Throughout this period,
as far as his family knew,
Ross' means of employment
was working on freelance
projects in computer finance.
- I am Rene Pinnell, age 29.
Today is December 6, 2012
and we are in the Jewish
Contemporary Art Museum,
and relationship to partner
is best friend.
So, Ross, how did you come
to live in San Francisco?
- Uh, you twisted
my arm until I said,
"Ah, fine I'll come."
[laughing]
I get a phone call from Rene,
"Ross, call me up.
I've got an opportunity
for you."
I'm like, "Okay."
He's like, "Yeah, I'm doing
a startup here in San Francisco.
Um, I want you to
be a part of it."
The more I thought about it,
and the more he, um,
laid out the pros
and cons, uh... uh...
the more it all just
seemed like cosmic
and the right thing to do.
So, um, yeah.
I bought my ticket
and two weeks later
I showed up at his doorstep.
- REEVES NARRATING: As Ross
Ulbricht was making his way
from Australia to Austin,
and eventually to San Francisco,
the Silk Road was online
and growing steadily.
So naturally it sparked
the attention
of federal law enforcement
and specifically
the wing of the DHS
called Homeland Security
Investigations,
housed in the old Customs House
in Baltimore, Maryland.
- You have postal
inspectors in Seattle
and Customs and Border
Protection, uh,
intercepting mail shipments
coming from overseas
full of drugs, full of,
uh, full of currency.
And one thing that happens is
they all lead
back to the Silk Road.
And you have a number
of independent investigations
sort of cropping up around
the same timeframe
following different leads,
but all leading back
to the same place.
- REEVES NARRATING:
At the same time,
the New York Cyber-Crime
Division of the FBI
began their own investigation,
headed by Agent Chris Tarbell.
- There were people
essentially online 24/7
as part of the team that...
that was monitoring,
gathering, even just the little
bits of evidence.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Informants were activated.
The site was crawling
with law enforcement
posing as vendors and buyers
from the very beginning
of Silk Road's existence.
In early 2012, HSI partnered
with Tarbell's FBI investigators
as well as the DEA to mount
an undercover operation
called "Marco Polo"
with the intention of
penetrating the inner
sanctum of the Silk Road.
- [digitally-altered voice]
- REEVES NARRATING:
The operation gained traction
when an undercover agent using
the vendor name of "nob"
was allegedly able to establish
direct communication
with the Dread Pirate Roberts,
which would lead to
a shocking turn of events.
Nob complained to DPR
about the small-fry nature
of most deals on the Silk Road.
"It really isn't worth it
to do below 10 kilos,"
the agent wrote.
DPR offered to help
find a buyer for nob
and allegedly turned to one
of his most trusted partners
known only as "chronicpain"
to put the deal together.
Chronicpain had been
one of the core administrators
of the Silk Road
from the beginning,
a frequent contributor
to the forums who shared
the Silk Road vision for
reducing harm in the drug trade.
But these halcyon days
were about to end.
In order to facilitate
this drug deal,
chronicpain gave the informant
his home address.
Federal agents immediately
apprehended chronicpain
at his Salt Lake City home
and were surprised to discover
that this 47-year-old family man
named Curtis Clark Green
was a dark net criminal.
- At some point they're going
to catch one of those people.
And what do you do
in a typical drug case?
You roll that person over
as a cooperating witness.
And in this case, one of them
they got really lucky
and he was an administrator
on the system.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Green had access to
other Silk Road users' accounts
and financial records,
including Dread Pirate Roberts.
"I have to assume he will sing,"
DPR wrote to nob,
the undercover agent.
"I'd like him beat up."
Then, the next day,
he allegedly wrote,
"Can you change the order to
execute rather than torture?"
A murder was staged.
And a photograph of Green's
bloody body was sent to DPR,
who paid for the hit in Bitcoin.
There would be five more alleged
Murders-For-Hire,
including ordered hits against
a blackmailer, a scammer
and an apparent contract
with the Hells Angels.
The names of two
of these victims
were found to be fictitious.
And authorities have no evidence
of any murders
being carried out.
The alleged attempted
murder of Curtis Green
allowed the authorities
to obtain an indictment
against Dread Pirate Roberts,
charging him with drug offenses,
attempted witness murder
and Murder-For-Hire.
Of course, they still
had no idea
who the Dread Pirate Roberts
actually was.
So the embedded agents continued
to communicate with DPR,
and DPR continued to respond.
In June of 2013,
Ross moved into an apartment
that he found on Craigslist.
Allegedly, he did not give
his roommates his real name
and was known as Joshua Terrey.
At the same time,
IRS agent Gary Alford
was investigating the Silk Road
and through a simple Google
search was able to locate
an early email on the open
internet discussing the launch
of the Silk Road marketplace
and connect that email to an
account owned by Ross Ulbricht.
One month later,
postal inspectors
at the Canadian border
seized a package of fake IDs
with Ross' image that were
en route to his home address.
Ross was visited at his
apartment by several DHS agents.
The agents handed Ross a false
California driver's license
that bore his picture,
but a different name.
Ulbricht denied ownership
or knowledge of the fake IDs,
and the agents simply left.
- If you suspect somebody
may be involved in a...
in a large-scale
criminal enterprise,
going and knocking on a door
with some, uh, you know,
some evidence of fake IDs
is important, uh,
because you can see
the guy face-to-face.
Uh, you may get some useful
information out of an interview.
You may or may not want to take
him into custody on the spot.
Let's sit back and let's, uh,
let's really go after this
in a... in a... you know, much
more global way, if you will,
uh, because there's a lot more
here than just one count of,
uh, you know, fake IDs.
- REEVES NARRATING: The next
big break in the case
would be achieved
by FBI agent Tarbell
and his cyber-crime team,
who had somehow located
the Silk Road servers
in Germany and Iceland.
How these hidden
servers were found
has been a matter
of controversy,
but the FBI had their own copy
of the Silk Road server,
and now they hoped to finally
unmask the Dread Pirate Roberts.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Over the course of a year,
a Chicago-based agent from the
DHS named Jared Der-Yeghiayan
had been embedded
in the Silk Road,
now posing as a high-ranking
moderator named "cirrus."
With both the evidence
connecting Ross to the launch of
the Silk Road and the incident
with the fake IDs,
Ross became one of
the primary suspects.
On October 1st in
a coordinated effort
between Der-Yeghiayan from
the DHS and Tarbell's FBI squad,
a sting operation was launched.
According to
Der-Yeghiayan's testimony,
he staked out Ross'
new residence.
And using his
pseudonym of cirrus,
Der-Yeghiayan initiated
a conversation
on the Silk Road with DPR.
Moments later, Ross went
to the Glen Park Library,
apparently to use their Wi-Fi.
And when Der-Yeghiayan
saw that DPR was logged back
into the Silk Road,
he gave the order for Tarbell
and his squad to move in.
- It's an excitement that you
couldn't even buy off Silk Road.
Uh, all the drugs you could buy
on the site, you... you... you...
It's not the same excitement
as catching the guy.
It's an adrenaline rush.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Ross was apprehended
before he could
encrypt his laptop.
He was allegedly logged into a
Silk Road administration panel
for customers
needing DPR's attention.
- He was a dream for drug users,
because he was very technically
adept and he was able to hide
both the website
that he put together
and the actual sales of illegal
drugs that the drug sellers
would, uh, make on his website.
- REEVES NARRATING: The Silk
Road was seized and shut down,
and charges were
announced against
a number of core partners
and vendors from the site.
Ross was held for over a month
in a jail in Oakland,
awaiting extradition
to New York.
Ross's family was able to raise
over a million dollars
for his bail.
But the prosecution argued
that due to the alleged
Murders-For-Hire, Ross was
too dangerous to release
and so his bail was denied.
- LYN ULBRICHT: I thought
it was the wrong decision.
He wouldn't have been a flight
risk and he's never been
and is not a danger to anyone.
- ALEX WINTER:
There was more than one person
using the DPR account?
- REEVES NARRATING:
The data seized from
the Silk Road servers included
all internal private messages,
which revealed that many people
collectively ran the site.
One vendor with the user
name "Variety Jones"
was active from the beginning
of the Silk Road.
Jones gave many of the orders
for running the Silk Road,
even instructing the systems
administrator to create
the Dread Pirate Roberts
persona.
But Ross Ulbricht remained
the primary focus
of the investigation.
Ross has been incarcerated
for over a year
in the Metropolitan
Detention Center
in Brooklyn awaiting trial.
Six weeks of that time was
in solitary confinement.
Ross plead not guilty and denies
being the Dread Pirate Roberts.
His trial was set for
November 10, 2014
in New York City.
If convicted, Ross faces
a minimum sentence of 30 years
with a maximum sentence
of life in prison.
- WOMAN: Are you taking a video?
- PINNELL: Mmm-hmm.
- ULBRICHT: He's a hairy fucker.
- PINNELL: These big guys
are generally not too, uh...
I would let him off somewhere.
- WOMAN: [gasps]
- PINNELL: Where is he?
- You know it's hard.
It's... it's hard on a family.
It really is, especially when
you love that person so much
and you believe in them so much
and you have such a daunting
Goliath of an opponent.
It's, uh, challenging.
It's kind of like a death,
in a way, when you go like,
"No, that can't be true,"
and then you're like,
"Oh, yeah, it's true."
And you go through
that kind of shock.
His dad, my husband,
um, of course,
he's trying to keep
our business going
so we have a livelihood.
And, um, his sister
is in, um, Australia
and she's been helping,
too, from there.
- I'm Ross' sister
and I can tell you
he has been a man of his word
and honor all his life.
I was shocked to hear
the news of his arrest,
but felt even more dismayed
at what the media was writing
about him, not even knowing him.
- LYN ULBRICHT: You know,
I read things by people
who have not a clue
who Ross really is.
He's been tried
and convicted in the media.
Nothing has been proven at all.
I don't know what's happened to
the presumption of innocence
in this country, but it is
a constitutional right here
that we are innocent
until proven guilty.
Ross sent me this picture of
himself about a week ago.
It was taken a couple of
weeks ago in prison.
I guess sometimes they go around
and take pictures
for the families.
He is doing well, uh, as well
as can be expected,
of course,
under the circumstances.
And finally, after
five months of delays,
he has had access
to the discovery,
the evidence that
the prosecution has.
And so he's been working very
hard going through that.
We are asking the,
uh, prosecution,
"How did you find the server,"
and they're not saying.
Um, we have to know how they
found the server in order to see
if Ross' Fourth Amendment
rights have been violated.
And how would anyone know
if the evidence had been
tampered with or anything else
if it's not revealed
how they found the server?
There were 14 searches
and seizures in this case,
which is a...
a fishing expedition
into a person's total property.
Unlimited rummaging through
all of their things
to see what they can find.
- When the criminal complaints
first appeared in... in October,
I think the supporters
of the Dread Pirate Roberts
and the Silk Road
just scattered.
Because suddenly this thing
that had seemed like
an idealistic community
built around non-violence
and, you know,
Libertarian free commerce,
suddenly seemed instead like
this bloody criminal conspiracy.
And a guy who probably otherwise
would have been a kind of, uh,
political cause célèbre,
who... who would have had
all of these supporters
calling for his freedom,
instead was treated as a...
was an immediate pariah.
He was seen as a criminal.
- So there's a lot of, um,
circumstantial, uh, evidence,
if you want to call it that.
There's a lot of technical bits
and pieces involved.
It got really crazy
in the middle of that.
Sort of one thing is taking down
this online drug market.
Another thing
is pinning a number of
Murders-For-Hires on top of it.
It just seems really,
really far-fetched.
- MALE NEWSCASTER:
The 29-year-old seemingly
clean-cut entrepreneur
was living a secret life
as a digital drug lord.
- They're claiming that he's
living in a manner of a...
of a head of a cartel.
The distinctions
between Ross Ulbricht
and the head of a cartel,
you don't have to see
too many movies to...
to recognize what
the differences are here.
- GREENBERG: Then when
the indictment finally came out,
there were suddenly
no charges around
these Murder-For-Hire
accusations,
only the drug trafficking
and money laundering
and computer hacking.
- They had six charges.
They used them against him
to deprive him of bail
and yet two and a half
months later, uh,
the prosecutor
didn't indict him.
What they did instead was they
called it an "uncharged crime."
Well, if something's a crime,
don't you charge someone for it?
And if it's not a crime,
why is it there...
Because it's
prejudicial to a jury
to have that sitting
there unproven just...
just smearing him.
- The portrayal they want
is of someone who they could
present to a jury
of not having redeeming value.
It's a way of poisoning
the atmosphere so that the jury
doesn't focus on the
allegations, but focuses on this
atmospheric that the government
has created that in some sense
is a diversion appealing to
the emotional aspect of it
so that if the proof is weak,
the benefit of the doubt
doesn't go to the defendant,
where it belongs, under
the presumption of innocence,
but it goes to
the government because,
hey, there are these awful
things lurking out there
which aren't part of what
we're supposed to find.
The government doesn't
have to prove them
beyond a reasonable doubt,
but they've injected them
in the case in a way
that is toxic to
an impartial evaluation of
what the evidence is on
the charged crimes.
So people come in with
a preconceived notion
and that's halfway
there to... to guilt.
- Previously, the Murder-
For-Hire was in there
as a charge and then
it was dropped.
But it's not gone away.
It's included as what
they call an overt act
in the conspiracy and...
to sell drugs.
And so they actually made it
one of the things to support
the larger drug conspiracy
to either get a trial
or get him to plead.
- It seemed like
this bait and switch
that the government had accused
him in this almost informal way
of murder so that when
he was charged with these
non-violent crimes in the end,
he would still be seen
as a violent criminal.
I think that that has
really been effective in...
in coloring the portrait
of Ross Ulbricht.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Ever since Ross' arrest,
he and his best friend
Rene Pinnell
have remained in
regular contact.
Rene declined to give
substantive interviews
to the press for fear they would
be used against Ross in court,
but agreed to answer
questions via email.
- WOMAN: [laughing]
- ULBRICHT:
♪ I'm a little teapot ♪
♪ Short and stout ♪
♪ Here is my handle
here is my spout ♪
♪ When I get all steamed up
hear me shout ♪
♪ Tip me over and pour me out ♪
- WOMAN [off camera] Yay!
- BOTH: [laughing]
- REEVES NARRATING: Because
of the severity of the charges,
Ross was not able to grant
an interview from prison,
which left only a scattering
of his personal
photographs and movies.
But from the exhaustive
discussions
with friends and family
and the public knowledge
of Ross's trajectory
from Physics
and Engineering major
to running a small home-spun
book-selling company,
it was difficult to understand
how he could possibly
have been the sole mastermind
of the Silk Road,
a vast and complex
internet service
with over a million
users worldwide.
Ross was certainly
bright and studious
with a deep interest in
Libertarian economic theory,
which clearly echoed
the mandate and philosophy
of many of the posts
of the Dread Pirate Roberts.
But he had no experience
whatsoever in computer coding
or scaling large
internet companies.
So how did Ross connect
to what little is truly known
about the Dread Pirate Roberts?
DPR was motivated
by a pacifistic philosophy
and an agenda of creating
victimless exchange
and reduced harm
in the drug trade.
This ethos would be embraced
by the chief architects
and vendors of the Silk Road
and reverberate through
the entire community.
- [digitally-altered voice]
- REEVES NARRATING:
The Silk Road appeared to be
a successful experiment in
creating a pacifistic community,
overseen by a figurehead with
a deep-rooted ideology.
But these core ideals of
the Dread Pirate Roberts
were completely at odds with
the Murder-For-Hire allegations.
Did DPR become corrupted
and turn his back on
the mandate of non-violence
and harm reduction?
Were there other people
using the DPR account
who were responsible
for these actions?
Or was there some other truth
behind these alleged
murder hits that
produced no victims?
- We don't know the first
piece of evidence
that lead the feds down
this chain of investigation
to the San Francisco library
where Ross Ulbricht
was arrested.
All we know is that
at some point they located
the Silk Road servers
in a data center
in Iceland and imaged them.
They copied all the data off
of them, and seized them,
but we don't know how
they found those servers.
The whole idea of... of
the Silk Road was that it ran
as a Tor-hidden service,
which means that Tor protected
its physical location
and made it very difficult
to locate the computers
that ran it.
So the mystery of how the FBI,
or the DEA, or possibly the NSA,
located those servers is still
unsolved and, in fact,
hasn't been mentioned in
any of the legal documents
surrounding
Ross Ulbricht's trial.
I think his defense has seized
on this as something
that the government
doesn't want to talk about.
And if that's the case,
then it does raise
these Fourth Amendment issues
of... of can the government
use essentially
hacking techniques
to dig up evidence on
a criminal suspect?
And if so, what kinds
of warrant do they need?
If in fact there was some
kind of violation of
the Fourth Amendment,
in that initial part
of the investigation,
that really was the first
clue that lead them
down this entire chain to
the arrest of Ross Ulbricht,
it could be a giant problem
for the prosecution that then
taints every other piece
of evidence that
they found subsequently.
- The government has
prosecuted other people
for doing essentially what the
government did here, which is...
trying to get underneath
the public face of a website.
And they have alleged that
getting that information
that's not supposed to
be publicly accessible
by sophisticated computer,
uh, inquiries or activities,
uh, that that is a...
a violation of federal law.
And that's why they always say,
we didn't do anything wrong,
we didn't do anything
in violation,
but they really know what's
stake here, because they've
actually prosecuted people
for the same thing.
And the government's affidavit,
the affidavit from Agent Tarbell
about how they got to
the Silk Road servers
has been met with
incredulousness
by the internet community.
- MAN: The Tarbell declaration,
to put it politely,
seems vaguely disconnected
from the truth.
If you... depending on which
security expert you ask,
you will get it's vaguely
disconnected to the truth
to something filled with...
it is a massive pile
of bovine excrement.
What Tarbell's story was is he
was typing away at his computer,
visiting the Silk Road website
and the CAPTCHA was
transmitted in the clear,
and he somehow
saw the IP packets
go directly to the server.
And so he then connects to that
server and gets the CAPTCHA.
Game over... they found
the backend server.
Unfortunately, this was playing
fast and loose with the truth.
Because the logs provided
to the defense show that
what Tarbell found was
not the CAPTCHA image,
but instead a php MyAdmin page.
The server was running some
stuff over the clear,
but not the CAPTCHA.
So Tarbell's story doesn't mesh
with the FBI's own evidence.
- MAN: They hacked the servers
and with that access
could essentially
do whatever they wanted.
Given just the institutional
pressure to...
to take this thing down,
it's naive to think
that they didn't.
- WILSON: Of course,
it's on the table
that this is how
they discovered him.
I mean he was dealing with Tor.
He was dealing with
all these technologies
which we know are the subject
of NSA investigations,
as revealed by Edward Snowden.
It's at least reasonable
to assume that there's been
this kind of parallel
construction or interference
or like not playing
by the rules that the state
deals out for you to play with.
But then again, we all know
that it deals the cards.
Uh, it... it runs
the game anyway.
It's... it's not even...
It's naive to think that this
wasn't an available option.
- SHIPLEY: The issue is whether
the agent could have done
what he said he did.
The theory that's been brought
forward in a testimony
by the individual
agents that did it,
they were able to manipulate
part of the server
to cough up an address that
shouldn't have been given up
and that address came
back to Iceland.
And that server there
was hosting
the Silk Road hidden service.
I think we're not gonna
know till we go to trial
and we may never know for sure.
- There's always this balance
of, uh, trying to be
forward leaning in your
investigative techniques
and making sure that you don't
trample on rights
at the same time.
You wanna stay well within the
bounds of your legal authority,
because if you step
over the line,
the evidence is gonna be tossed.
It's not gonna be
admissible in court
and you may wind up, uh,
jeopardizing the outcome
of an entire investigation.
And so I think what agencies
will try and do is they'll...
they'll want to step
right up to the line,
and maybe get a little bit
of chalk on their toes,
but don't step over it.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Ross' lawyer made a motion
to dismiss the case based
on the disputed seizure
of the Silk Road servers,
arguing that admitting this
material not only violates
his client's
Fourth Amendment rights,
but would set
a dangerous precedent
for the rights to privacy
of all citizens.
The judge, Katherine Forest,
sided with the prosecution
stating that the Tarbell
declaration was acceptable.
And the motion was denied.
Search and seizure law
in the digital age
is really, uh, doesn't have
the limitations on it that,
um, it does in
the physical space.
And um, we see it not only in
the search and seizure laws,
like what is
the standard upon which
they can come and grab
your computer?
Um, what kind of
searches can they do
on your computer
once they have it?
Do they just get everything?
We see this at the border.
Or we see this at
searches into arrests.
People now carry
around smart phones
that have their whole
lives in them.
And if they get stopped,
law enforcement is...
is certainly right now in a lot
of places taking the position
that absolutely anything
that's connected,
that's on that device, including
logging into your accounts
that you can log into from
that device, is fair game.
- If the prosecution gets away
with this warrantless seizure
of Americans' data as well as
all these other foreigners,
it could have a lasting
precedent for how
the Fourth Amendment works
in the digital age.
I think that that, in fact,
may be the most lasting
effect of the Silk Road.
- Generally, what happens
in the criminal law field
is that there's a... some case
of... of major proportion
that is used as a means
of changing rules,
or expanding exceptions to
constitutional protections,
and once it's there,
once the precedent is set,
it then trickles down very
quickly and very easily
into all sorts of
ordinary cases where,
you know, the ends
justify the means.
Then all of a sudden,
it's now spread.
- The average citizen may say,
"Well, why is this
important to me?
"Why do I care?
"I'm not buying drugs
on the network.
Nobody I know is buying
drugs on the network,"
but it's not just about that.
We're a democracy and informed
citizens, uh, um,
understand they have
a right to privacy
and that the Fourth Amendment
protects against
unreasonable searches
and seizures.
Information has to be encrypted.
And that goes from
a large corporation
down to an individual.
And so for those who
are arguing that information
should not be encrypted,
certainly that makes it easier
for law enforcement
to, um... combat,
but it also makes it easier for
the cyber criminals to attack.
- It makes total sense
that criminals
are among the early wave,
along with the sort
of paranoid people,
of these new tools and services.
But that doesn't mean that
they're the only people
using these services.
You know, there are a hell of
a lot of journalists
that I know and regularly
communicate with now over Tor.
But you know, for the people
who oppose this technology,
who see it as a threat,
the fact that criminals use it
is a great way to...
to demonize it.
- I definitely do believe
that there are people
in the US that don't think
that the government
is doing anything wrong.
It's not necessarily something
that you're concerned with
or that you care too much about
or that you're really
passionate about until you...
you're standing right
in the middle of it.
- And it's something
more dangerous
than any website could ever be
is what our government has
become and how they operate.
- This goes back to that
question of the government
kind of trying to treat the
internet differently without,
uh, following the same kind of,
uh, judicial processes.
- Well the Supreme Court has
proven that they do not agree.
You know, recently with
Riley vs California
with an illegal search
of a cell phone.
Precedent can be set
that will limit their ability
to infringe on our rights.
- SANDVIK: Someone asked how her
political views have shifted.
Because suddenly she's standing
right in the middle of Tor,
Bitcoin, the war on drugs,
online anonymity, encryption.
And she's had a... she's had to
learn a lot of different things,
and also not only just the whole
legal system but, uh,
everything around
the technology and the case.
- CROWD: [applauding]
- REEVES NARRATING:
After over a year in prison,
Ross delayed
the trial two months,
stating that important
discovery evidence
he needed to examine
had only just been delivered
to him by the prosecution.
The FBI shut down
what it calls
the most sophisticated and
extensive criminal marketplace
on the internet, but it may
be finding new life.
- REEVES NARRATING:
The arrest of Ross Ulbricht
and closure of the Silk Road
did nothing to hamper
drug sales on the dark net.
Many new markets
immediately appeared,
including a re-launch of
the Silk Road itself,
also run by someone
calling themselves
the Dread Pirate Roberts.
And like its predecessor,
the second Silk Road
also claimed a mandate
of reducing violence
and harm in drug transactions.
- MALE NEWSCASTER:
The Dread Pirate tweets,
"Silk Road while under
my watch will never harm a soul.
If we did, then we are no better
than the thugs on the street."
- The new Dread Pirate Roberts
told me that he knows
he can't be around forever,
and when he's gone,
someone else... he's
confident someone else
will step up and fill the void.
You can take down the man, but
you can't take down the idea.
- REEVES NARRATING: By this
time, statistics appeared
claiming the first Silk Road
had succeeded in its mission
of reducing violence
in the drug trade.
- MAN: While I was with
the Baltimore Police Department
in the early 2000s,
I had two city
officers in uniform
killed by drug dealers
on the street.
And there was a family of seven,
the Dawson family
on Preston Street,
they were killed by one drug
dealer in one night...
Mother, father and five kids.
And so as the years in the early
2000s start moving along,
I'm continuing to think about
this from a place of violence
and beginning to realize that
our policies of drug prohibition
were actually counterproductive
to public safety.
The one thing that I signed
on for to improve,
to better public safety
in our neighborhoods,
was making it worse.
And, uh, I found a large number
of police officers and judges
and criminal prosecutors
and DEA agents
and FBI who think the same way.
If Baltimore moved from street
corners to online services,
oh, my God, do you know
how many shootings,
how many fewer shootings
we would have every year,
which equate to fewer homicides?
Number one, it removes the...
the buyer from the back alleys
and from the street corners
and from those dangerous places
of dealing with the seller.
Buying it over the internet
where it's delivered to you,
removes you from that scenario.
- Well, one of the interesting
things that having
an online market
does is that it makes
sellers much more
accountable to buyers.
And one of the really
interesting innovations
is the whole review system,
where buyers can review
the sellers and the items
that they bought from these,
uh, on these market places.
And what that does is it makes
sellers more accountable
and it lets buyers...
It gives buyers a way
to assess both the quality,
the purity and the potency of
the drugs they're getting.
It makes, uh, these transactions
much more safe for the buyers.
- But we're shutting them down,
attempting to shut them down,
because we will
never shut them down.
We've been at this drug war
now for over four decades,
and what has happened
since then?
At the beginning,
it was just the cartels
and organized crime
making a ton of money.
Today, they make globally
$322 billion off this industry.
Corporate America's
also now in the game.
Private prisons, okay?
Corrections Corporation
of America.
About a year ago they gave out
$675 million in dividends
to the shareholders.
Drug testing companies.
It's now become
a multi-billion-dollar industry.
And who gets tested?
Those who are in prison
or under the control
of our criminal
justice programs...
On parole and probation.
So corporate America's
making a lot of money.
What about law enforcement?
Law enforcement's
making a ton of money.
The government's
1033 Program, you know,
where we get armored
vehicles and machine guns
and whatever we want of
the surplus military equipment...
That's because of the drug war.
- Over the years we've seen
these... these huge bureaucracies
build up around the drug war,
around prosecuting the drug war.
You've got
the Drug Enforcement Agency.
You've got the Office of
National Drug Control Policy.
So a lot of the... a lot of
the opposition is just rooted in
self interest among places
like the FBI and the DEA,
where if you're telling somebody
who's been in the FBI
for 30 years that drugs
are no longer a priority,
that's an existential
threat to them.
That kind of takes away their
whole reason for existence.
- You really have to think about
the danger of some
of these drugs,
the severe danger of addiction,
uh, the havoc that it, you know,
that it reaps on families
and, you know, and children,
and, uh, careers.
And so to say that, you know,
we need to step back
and liberalize,
well, but you... that's one
approach you can take,
but then you've got to look
at a cause and effect.
If we do this, what are the
second and third order effects?
- FRANKLIN: The FBI,
our federal government,
they're gonna go in and they're
shutting these places down.
But you know what?
New ones just open up.
'Cause there's so much
money to be made.
They'll continue to open up,
and it's just
a dog chasing its tail.
- KIRK ULBRICHT: We're a team,
and we've been working on
this thing together
right from the start.
The way it's affected me
is in some ways
very much the same
as it affects Lyn,
but I don't have to go out
there and talk to reporters.
And we've... we've kind
of set it up that way.
- It's hard enough having
your... your loved one in prison,
but then the whole media thing
is, it definitely adds pressure.
- I've known for a long time
that the media wasn't
reporting the whole story,
that it was skewed.
I see what Lyn and I are doing
as a, um, as a pushback to that.
- Ross has been in
there a year and he's...
he's avoided all violence,
even though it's
been around him.
That has matured him for sure.
The fact that he's come out
of this unscathed so far,
uh, speaks volumes.
- LYN ULBRICHT:
He seems serious.
You know, there's
a lot at stake.
He's, uh, feeling good
that we got the extension.
He had this mountain
of stuff to go through
and I felt like he was
running out the clock.
And now they have that
extra two months has made...
has been "essential"
is the word he used.
And so I think
he feels that, you know,
he's... he's much more
prepared and... and ready.
- Yeah, he says he's
ready for trial.
He's ready to go
in there and win.
I have also matured
in this last year.
Matured in my thinking
about ethics, politics.
When I became
more and more aware of
what the drug war
was doing, the tragedy.
So many people have been
victimized by the drug war.
It's a giant mess and it's
a story that needs telling.
And we... we've got a pulpit,
in a way, to tell it from.
- It's so weird to be doing
all this and it's...
it's distracting and it's...
it's challenging
and you wanna do
the right thing,
and then it's all about Ross.
And then we go and we see him
and hug him and talk to him
and hold his hand and it's
just like Ross, you know?
It's such a disconnect, and, uh,
it's just so hard to
see him in there.
- KIRK ULBRICHT:
Being in the prison, visiting,
it's a very emotional
experience,
because there are all
these families there
and they get to see their
loved one one hour a week.
And so they're soaking
each other up.
And you're in a room
of 150 people,
sitting side-by-side,
tight-packed.
And, uh, there's just
all this emotion
saturating the atmosphere.
- KIRK ULBRICHT: The prisoners
have segregated themselves.
But as loved ones coming to
visit, there's no sense of,
uh, segregation, um,
race at all.
We're just 150 people whose
hearts are breaking.
- SOGHOIAN: Of all
the Snowden disclosures
that have come out to date,
the one that will have
the greatest long-term impact
is the revelation that the NSA
has been subverting
cryptographic standards and
making the internet less secure.
That disclosure, those articles,
have radicalized
a new generation
of cryptographers,
of computer scientists
who are now intent upon
building tools and services
that can withstand pervasive
government surveillance.
- Did you see our wireless
from Barclay's Bank?
They like Bitcoin, so they're
supporting our work.
They're providing us with
free Wi-Fi from the bank.
- REEVES NARRATING:
In the fall of 2014,
as Ross was preparing
for his trial,
a group of hackers,
programmers and activists
met in a squat in
the center of London.
This gathering represented
the next wave of the dark net,
developing new and evolved
cryptographic tools
that would not be
so easily shut down.
- Open source
is incredibly powerful.
Open source is responsible for
WikiLeaks, Wikipedia, Linux,
which runs all of our...
our infrastructure, for Firefox,
for Bit Torrent, for Bitcoin,
for all of these,
for encryption, for all of
these real uses of tech...
Not the yuppie, uh,
Angry Birds or silly apps that,
that these people,
make, you know?
Open source is also an example
of how we can organize
economically, an example
for the future, to...
to build the products we need
without needing
proprietary industry,
the points of control,
without needing masters
and slaves and babysitters.
- SOGHOIAN: It's not enough to
build privacy-preserving tools.
It's not enough to write
revolutionary research papers
and design amazing
cryptographic primitives.
You have to get them into
the hands of the users.
And I think in the future
what you'll find is that
tools like Tor, tools like OTR,
like PGP, like Bitcoin
will be built into the services
and applications that you use
and you won't know
they're there.
- TAAKI: We want to empower
the individual,
protect the small guy.
We have a mistrust
of central authority.
We believe in freedom
of information.
First of all,
we have the centralized
drug marketplace, Silk Road.
Governments went in
and shut that down.
And then up sprouted
dozens of different,
centralized drug markets.
And in a game of whack a mole,
they shut down one
and now there's dozens.
And now we're entering the realm
of decentralized drug markets,
with no central operator,
no central point of control.
What are they gonna do?
- SHIPLEY: They're gonna
continue to do
these kinds of things, and even
if it's a distributed network,
peer-to-peer is worked
continuously by the, uh,
state and local law
enforcement agencies.
And they arrest
people every week.
- REEVES NARRATING:
On November 6, 2014,
law enforcement agencies
around the world
launched a coordinated effort
called "Operation Onymous,"
seizing hundreds
of dark net sites,
including the re-launch
of the Silk Road.
- GREENBERG: Bruce Schneier,
the cryptographer,
once said to me,
"You know, in this
cat and mouse game,
the mice will win in the end,
but the cats will be well fed."
I think that that's
the way to see it.
That, uh, this game is going
to continue forever.
- WILSON: There's a reason
the Silk Road was so powerful.
And I... and I know the cryptos
now are writing
the kind of automatic Silk Road,
and Amir helped do this.
This is now the peer-to-peer
model where there's
no one individual administrator.
And seeing that as the weak
point, technically speaking,
this is all correct.
But there... there's
something kind of...
I don't want to make him
a hero, like a...
I don't want to say
that he's a hero.
But you know, DPR recognized
what was at stake
and he was willing to do
the things that most of
the Libertarians
weren't willing to do,
because he was serious about, I
think what the Silk Road meant.
- REEVES NARRATING:
Three weeks before the trial,
the issue of the Murders-
For-Hire suddenly resurfaced.
The prosecution announced that
due to these allegations,
they would not allow
Ross's defense to know
the identities of
their witnesses.
The defense responded that using
these uncharged crimes
in these manner was prejudicial.
A hearing was called
to resolve the matter.
- LYN ULBRICHT: The judge ruled
that some of the witnesses
won't be made available
to the defense
until right before the trial.
It's based on her saying
that Ross might intimidate
or even murder people,
um, from jail.
- WILSON: When all this
first happened, I said,
well, it would still have been
necessary to say that, well,
this man's a murderer and...
and he was only out
for his own gain.
And you know, he had...
what do you call it,
a callous disregard
for human life.
It's necessary to paint
a figure that way
rather than to make him,
you know, a martyr of the...
the war on drugs.
I think that's just
good planning.
- I think it's gonna
be difficult, um,
to have a fair trial.
If you are innocent
until proven guilty,
then with all the evidence
and all the stories
that have been written,
I think it's gonna be
really difficult to...
to find people who are
not influenced by...
by any of this
at all going into it.
- REEVES NARRATING:
The day before the trial,
Ross provided a written
statement.
It was the closest anyone would
ever get to an actual interview.
- MALE NEWSCASTER: Ross Ulbricht
went on trial today.
A jury will decide a case
that could impact the future
of internet privacy.
- Good evening to you.
Opening arguments
taking place today,
and the first witness
took the stand
and actually just got
off a few minutes ago...
A Homeland Security
investigation special agent
who testified saying that,
"Thousands of envelopes
of drugs..."
- GREENBERG: I think everyone
was surprised that Ross Ulbricht
and his lawyers took this
to trial in the first place
instead of just
taking a plea deal
like pretty much
everyone expected.
And today, we saw why,
which is that they've actually
got a pretty compelling
alternate narrative of how this
whole case has played out.
The story that Dratel
is telling that Ross did create
the Silk Road, which is an
amazing admission to begin with,
and that the real operator
of the Silk Road,
the Dread Pirate Roberts,
framed him.
It's a kind of theory that
I never heard posed before,
that instead of Ross being
the Dread Pirate Roberts,
he was framed by him.
But in many ways, you know, it's
something I should've expected
because it's what
the Dread Pirate Roberts told me
when I interviewed
him in July of 2013
that he didn't create
the Silk Road,
that he had inherited
it from its creator,
kind of like a business
acquisition.
The FBI has told me that that
was Ross Ulbricht lying to me.
If it is a lie, it would
require just a lot of...
a lot of foresight and planning,
kind of like the...
you know, an amazing game
of chess or something.
- REEVES NARRATING:
In the first days of the trial,
the prosecution presented
evidence that Ross
kept a journal on his laptop
describing his involvement
in the Silk Road and that the
Bitcoins seized from his laptop
came directly from the site.
While the defense would argue
that Ross abandoned
the Silk Road after creating
it and that the journal
and the Bitcoin were
planted on his laptop.
- MALE NEWSCASTER:
Andy, you interviewed
the Dread Pirate Roberts.
What's the evidence connecting
Dread Pirate Roberts
to Ulbricht directly?
- GREENBERG: Well, in the first
couple of weeks of this trial,
which is ongoing now,
we've seen that the prosecution
has a very strong case.
Once they seized his laptop,
they found that
he had kept a journal.
If this is, in fact,
Ulbricht's journal.
His defense claims it's not.
- Right.
- He documented
the administration
of this site for years.
He has a log book
of daily activities.
So this is a really tight
case that's gonna be
very difficult for Ulbricht
to... to squeeze out of it.
- Underneath, in the deep web,
we have an area
where this young man,
according to the government,
has made a decision that
he's going to run
an illegal drug empire
and we need to stop you,
swift and certain prosecution,
and ultimate certain punishment.
- REEVES NARRATING:
As the trial continued,
Dratel planned to reveal
the government's own evidence
showed they suspected multiple
people of running the Silk Road.
During his cross examination of
DHS agent Der-Yeghiayan,
Dratel was able to expose that
the agent had long suspected
another person to be
the Dread Pirate Roberts,
going so far as to seek
a warrant for this suspect.
The protection protested this
entire line of questioning
on the grounds that
it was hearsay.
The judge sided
with the prosecution
and Dratel was no longer
allowed to question
government witnesses about
alternate suspects
that came from
the government's own evidence.
When the time came for Dratel
to begin his defense,
he intended to use
expert witnesses
to explain that
the complex technology
behind encryption
and cryptocurrency
made it difficult to prove
that the journal and
the Bitcoin belonged to Ross.
The prosecution objected
to these witnesses,
claiming they should have been
made known earlier in the trial
and they were not necessary
for the jury's understanding
of the case.
Once again, the judge sided
with the prosecution,
stating that this case did not
require specialized knowledge.
Without expert witnesses
and unable to pursue
the government's own evidence
of an alternate DPR,
Dratel's entire defense
was effectively blocked.
The trial ended abruptly
the next day.
The trial of Ross Ulbricht
raised more questions
than it answered.
Did we really know the full
truth of the Silk Road case?
Would this case set a precedent
for the warrantless search of
Americans' digital property?
Whatever the ultimate outcome,
it was clear that
the fall of the Silk Road
was not the end of a chapter,
but the beginning.
And the movement to create tools
and services for online privacy
is stronger than ever.
- FEMALE NEWSCASTER: The trial
of Silk Road mastermind
Ross Ulbricht concluded
when a jury found him guilty
on seven different counts
that included three drug charges
as well as computer hacking,
money laundering
and even a kingpin charge
of continuing a criminal
enterprise.
Ulbricht faces a minimum
of 30 years behind bars,
but his defense plans
to appeal this decision.
- Anyone here, all of us,
are going to be judged
by things for which
there is no attribution
in real life.
There's only attribution
on the internet
for things to be created,
codified, edited, moved, hacked.
- MAN: Was it a fair trial?
- No, I don't think so.
- GREENBERG: As the actual
verdict was read,
the word "guilty"
was said seven times.
Ross was just staring
straight ahead.
I don't know what
was on his face.
But afterwards he turned
back to look at his family
and he had this really
heartbreaking
kind of stoic smile.
And he was just...
he wasn't crying,
but he was just blinking...
like blinking hard.
And, uh, then as he was led
away, his mom said,
"This is not the end."
You know, that was it.
- GREENBERG:
The evidence against Ulbricht
was so powerful and Dratel's
strategy had been
to try to cross examine
every government witness
and to pull out
his alternative story
through that cross examination.
And when the judge essentially
shut that down and said
you have to limit your cross
examination to the scope
of the government's
initial questioning,
that really prevented him from
telling any other story.
- KIRK ULBRICHT: We have
a much more informed perspective
than the rest of the world.
Uh, we have meetings
that we've had with Josh
through the last year and three
months, uh, regular meetings.
We know about how he felt like
he might win the case,
uh, in cross examination.
Uh, we know that the government,
that his witnesses were...
were, uh, blocked
from testifying.
Um, we were in the courtroom
and we saw what happened and...
and the... the, uh, the travesty,
the, uh, appalling,
um, obstruction of justice
that happened.
- There was 5,000 pages
of government evidence
to do with one witness alone,
Jarod Der-Yeghiayan.
None of that was allowed.
5,000 pages, and it was
dumped on the defense
10 days before trial.
Another 2,500 pages for other
witnesses was dumped
on the defense
a week before trial.
And it was full of
exculpatory evidence
favorable to Ross that was
not permitted to be used.
- All this great,
huge field of evidence
that came out in the 3,500
material, a week before trial,
that was...
[clears throat]
that would help
prove Ross's innocence
was excluded from being brought
out in the courtroom.
It would have been
a whole different case.
This was the trial
that didn't happen.
- The trial that didn't happen.
- The trial just didn't
happen, because it was only
the prosecution's
narrative that we heard.
- WINTER: So then what
about the hacking
of the Silk Road servers?
What about the precedent
issue of the case?
- We didn't get that far.
You know, we didn't get to even
have that kind of public hearing
where the FBI has to
say how they did it
and then we get to decide
whether that was
legal or illegal.
That's maybe the most
frustrating thing about this
case from a legal point of view
is that American law enforcement
hacked a foreign server,
I believe,
and they didn't have a warrant
and they completely got away
with it and nobody's even...
nobody even gets to ask any
questions about it.
- WINTER: How is Ross
through all of this?
- He's an amazing guy.
You know, he's handling this
so much better than I would've.
I...I don't know how I could've
taken what he's, uh,
put up with and
been subjected to
in this last year
and three months.
And we pray that, uh...
[sighing]
his spirit won't be
crushed by this.
- GREENBERG: It seems that Ross
conceived of the Silk Road,
that he ran it for its
entire existence online.
I actually accept that
the government has proven that.
But Ross Ulbricht is
a fascinating character.
He invented
this brilliant thing.
He had principles.
He wasn't just a cyber-criminal.
He wasn't just a drug lord
or a kingpin
as he's described
in these charges.
He was also an idealistic guy.
And I'm gonna be conflicted
about both the kind of virtue of
the Silk Road and of
Ross Ulbricht as a person,
I think, for the rest
of my life.
I'm not gonna be able to come
to a conclusion about this.
GOT ANY MORE QUESTIONS
OR SHOULD WE WRAP IT UP?
YES.
WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO DO OVER
THE NEXT FIVE YEARS?
IN ONE SENTENCE.
I'M GOING TO DO A FEW THINGS
BUT ONE SENTENCE ISN'T ENOUGH.
I'M PRETTY SURE I WANT TO START A FAMILY
IN THE NEXT FIVE YEARS.
NICE. OKAY.
AND... YEAH, MAKE MORE FRIENDS
AND CLOSE PEOPLE I LOVE.
FOCUS ON BEING MORE CONNECTED TO
PEOPLE.
AND 20 YEARS?
20 YEARS.
I WANT TO HAVE HAD A
SUBSTANTIAL, POSITIVE IMPACT
ON THE FUTURE OF HUMANITY
BY THAT TIME.
DO YOU THINK YOU'RE GOING TO
LIVE FOREVER?
I THINK IT'S A POSSIBILITY
I HONESTLY DO.
I THINK I MIGHT LIVE FOREVER IN SOME FORM
BY THAT TIME
WITH TECHNOLOGIES CHANGING SO FAST.
COOL I HOPE I'M GOING THERE.
SWEET.